When you go to buy health insurance, there is a
lot of confusion and one
confusion is whether there is an individual plan
or a family floater plan. So, for this, it is
important to understand what is the difference between the two.
You have very commonly
said that whenever you are collecting from the plan
online through an agent, then
through the insurance company, there you
see whether you want an individual plan or a
family floater plan. So,
in the big picture, we will talk about the difference between the two.
What is the difference between which one
is better to buy and what is the difference in the premium of both. We will
understand it with an example. So,
before starting the video, I would
like to introduce myself. My name is
Gurleen Kaur Chikku. I am a Certified
Financial Planner. I have been
associated with the insurance industry for the last 17 years
and every week I bring videos for you so that the
journey of insurance on your personal financial life becomes easy and happy
because this is also the tagline of our company. Let's move
towards the video. Difference Between  Individual
and family floater plans and which one you should buy, first of all
what is the definition of
individual health insurance and family,
so individual health insurance
is an definition, from the name itself it is clear that
individual policy means the
premium for the time period in the policy is being
charged on the life of the individual, so
if you are taking a policy only for yourself then it will be
called individual health insurance, otherwise
if you are taking a family policy then
it will be called family floater, so basically it is an umbrella policy that includes
all the family members under the umbrella,
in individual, umbrella is used by
single person, whereas in family floater, the
entire family is under the umbrella, so it is an easy
example to understand, anyone
definitely needs a family floater, so they
can share that policy, so the time period will be
shared by the policy holder and the
premium will also be charged accordingly, now let's talk about the
coverage in individual plan  There
is coverage from the policyholder, if you have taken a policy of 10 lakhs
for an individual,
then if they need hospital treatment, then they
can avail the entire 10 lakhs themselves. How is the coverage done in a family floater? If you have
taken a coverage of 10 lakhs in a family floater, then how is that 10 lakhs coverage? If there is a
coverage of 10 lakhs and there are
people in the family below, then if anyone needs it, then he can avail it from the
family floater. So,
as we
said, it is being shared between the
policyholders, if there is a policy of 10 lakhs and
one family member avails it for ₹5, then the
remaining ₹5 lakhs is back.
Whatever coverage is there for the entire family is being shared, only then it is
free according to the policyholders. Later, we
will talk about free and again, you already know
that this is applicable in the policy period, so for
one year, it gets replenished again after one year, so suppose
you have done it in this year  You have done it and
whether it is an individual plan or a family floater plan,
next time you renew the policy, that plan will
again be added to your policy.
Now let's talk about the advantage of
buying an individual or a
family plan. The biggest advantage of buying an individual plan is that the
entire time limit is there for you. Even now,
whether the problem is 20 lakhs or 50
lakhs, you know that the entire
time limit is available to you. You can use it
in one policy period. The advantage
of a family floater plan is that you will get
cost effectiveness. Just like
in an individual plan, you are paying the cost of an individual,
whereas in a family floater, because you are
sharing the tax, the cost will be comparatively less.
Now, compared to an individual plan, let's
talk about the disadvantage of
buying an individual plan or a
small family plane. The disadvantage is that the
cost is higher in an individual plan,
compared to a family floater plan
because  If you are single and have
individual coverage in your name then the cost is higher as compared to
family floater
plans which have tax of Rs. 10
lakhs, if family members are sharing the tax then it is not
enough for such people, then
10 lakh insurance will not be enough for such people,
so to get the advantage in this way,
in individual you can take only as much coverage as
you need as per your convenience and individual
plan is suitable for those who
are single, for them the
coverage will be concentrated and mostly you
can also see for senior citizens that
what happens by taking individual coverage is that on average
they definitely have to pay more in senior citizens,
so there that individual coverage reduces your cost more
and if you are a
family, if you are already in a family like husband, wife and
children then it is recommended for you to
take family floater plan,
what will happen in it is that you take more coverage among all,
as I said that if he  The
disadvantage is that the policy is not BF in the tax, so
what are you doing in this, you can
take more than 10%
coverage, but higher coverage, there is a big
option for everyone from which they can choose it
whenever required, so that you understand
what is the difference in premium, this is just to give an
example, this is not the premium of any company, to
give an example
how individual and floater policies reduce the policy, if
you take an individual policy and are 37 years old, you have taken a
10% policy, it
comes for free Rs 12000, if we take the same policy as a
family floater, if you are
husband and wife, they both take it, if you are
37 years old, then the 10% coverage is available
here for free Rs 17000,
so you see that the premium of an individual was Rs
12000 and for two people it is Rs 17000, that
means it has not doubled because it is not
24%.
This 17000, so what is happening now, the tax of
10 lakhs here will be
shared between two people instantly, in the first example it is
of a single individual, here I would
like to introduce you to another concept which is called multi individual,
what is multi individual,
in a single policy two people bring forward an individual tax,
like here we are sharing 10 lakhs,
so there is also an option that
you can take a multi individual policy,
in a single policy two people like husband and wife,
we talked about 37 and 35 individuals
bringing their 10 lakhs each, what will be the benefit of it, of course, so
its benefit will be that
if you take a multi individual policy,
then
in this example here we talked about first
individual premium shoe premium 12000
family photo premium which is 17000, now
we will talk about multi policy, they want to treat
both of them separately  And if they are
in a single policy, the premium of 10 LK multi individual
policy is 19400, so it is also a good
thing that those who are family floaters are
paying only ₹2000 extra, but you are
getting individual, so multi plan, it is also a
very good option, so you
can consider that also, for family, so just to
conclude individual plans are
good for those who are individuals and
for senior citizens also you
can see individual plans, if you want to see the visual for them, then it is also a
good option for heavy
jewellery, they are doing it separately because they
definitely have more tax, next
floater, where there is a family, then you
can take a family floater plan, if there is a couple and
they have children, then they can go in family floater plan,
so the problem in family floater is that
you can take more premium because
you are already paying premium from IIT,
where you do not have to pay 2x, you have to
pay less than individual, so you  You
can consider taking more than one sub-inspection shot.
If your plan was to take 10 lakhs, then do
it by 2015. Defending on where you
live and what your needs are,
you can increase it on that basis. Ultimately, you should
not go above 100% premium. After seeing the premium,
you should take it for individual or
I should definitely assess what your needs are.
How much tax do you need. Note
only today, think ahead that
if any disease comes in future or there is a hospital, then
how much insurance will be sufficient.
Very soon I am going to bring a video on this also
with proper calculations on how you
can calculate your health insurance tax.
And regarding this, whatever questions you have about individual and family,
you can
ask in the comment section. You can write to us on
email ID or WhatsApp number.
A reminder before going, if
you have not yet subscribed to our channel, do
subscribe so date you get the right
information. Thank you. So match 17
late se
kab akele sher  are doing